Speaker 1: Hey everybody, Peter Zion here, coming from Italy. It's a monastery that was built around a hermit
Speaker 1: hole probably in the 8th century, then it was remodeled in the 11th, and then in the 14th,
Speaker 1: you get the idea reused. Lots of things in Italy are like that. Anyway, that reminds me of what's
Speaker 1: going on right now in Poland. The Hungarian Prime Minister, Peter Magyar, Peter, good name,
Speaker 2: had made his first foreign trip to Warsaw to meet with the Prime Minister of Poland, Donald Tusk.
Speaker 2: Now, let's talk about what this isn't and then talk about what it is. So what it isn't
Speaker 2: is a political alliance that has to do with how the elections went. No, no, no, no, no. Peter Magyar
Speaker 1: is center-right, strongly right, I might underline, and the person he kicked out of power, Victor Orban,
Speaker 1: supposedly was also center-right, but was really just breathlessly corrupt and would bow down to
Speaker 1: anyone who wasn't Brussels. And now that he's gone, a number of his former ministers have actually fled
Speaker 1: the country because they know they're going to be put into jail. And we're going to have a series of
Speaker 2: parliamentary votes in Hungary that basically strips the ones that are left of any power.
Speaker 2: So it's a real transition, but from corruption to conservatism, not from conservatism to liberalism.
Speaker 2: On the Polish side of the equation, Donald Tusk is an avowed pan-Europeanist. He used to be an
Speaker 2: uppity-up in European power structures before he went back home and became prime minister. He's of the
Speaker 2: center-left. And so the two of them on domestic political issues have a lot of things they argue
Speaker 2: about. But that's not the point, because what this is, is more of a strategic alliance.
Speaker 2: You see, Poland and Hungary, along with the Czech Republic and Slovakia, form a group called the
Speaker 2: Visegrad Group, which is four countries that tend to coordinate their operations at the EU level.
Speaker 2: But for most of the last decade, they haven't. In part because Viktor Orban became more and more and
Speaker 2: more correct and more and more and more pro-Russian and less and less and less pro-European. And also
Speaker 2: because there were political evolutions in Poland where the nationalists were in power before Donald
Speaker 2: Tusk for quite some time. And they just found it difficult to get along. That's probably behind us now.
Speaker 2: I don't want to say it's perfect because we have a guy by the name of Robert Fico in Slovakia who's a little
Speaker 2: a little odd, but not nearly as odd as some of the others have been in the last 10 years.
Speaker 2: Why does this matter? The European Union doesn't necessarily work on consensus. They have a weighted
Speaker 2: majority voting system among their council of ministers, that's the council of prime ministers,
Speaker 2: that is nauseatingly complicated. But the short version is, to get anything passed,
Speaker 2: a certain number of countries have to agree, and those countries have to represent a certain
Speaker 2: percentage of the population. And if you take Poland and Slovakia and Hungary and Czech Republic,
Speaker 2: and you bunch them together into a single voting bloc, they have actually more voting power,
Speaker 2: because they're four countries, than France or Italy, two of the three big states in the EU,
Speaker 2: and they have about the same population. So this doesn't mean that the central Europeans are going to
Speaker 2: suddenly start getting their way on everything, but it does mean now that they can really duke it out
Speaker 2: with the major established advanced powers on an equal basis from a decision-making point of view.
Speaker 2: Plenty of things to worry about. The primary one for everyone right now is, of course, Russia and
Speaker 2: the Ukraine war. And with Orban gone, there's a lot more room for consensus. And when you get past that
Speaker 2: and start talking about the nitty-gritty things of day-to-day government, like say, budgets,
Speaker 3: now we've got the central Europeans who can actually stand up for themselves and get some things done.
Speaker 3: So all in all, reasonable first trip. Looks like it's been a smashing success. Nobody stabbed anybody.
Speaker 3: And in Europe these days, that's great.